Omar Samman

sammanomar@hotmail.com

Mobile: +49-170-2671177 (Personal)

Germany, Erlangen

PROFILE

Proficient in HTML, CSS, JavaScript, SQL, experienced in data processing/manipulation languages such as SAS, R and Python. Experience with data visualization in Tableau, Power BI, Excel, or others. Proficient in use of Microsoft Office software, including Excel, Word, and Power Point. A creative regional finance/sales and market analyst with over 3 years of experiences in JCI Dubai. Excellent quantitative and analytical skills with an aptitude for problem solving.

OBJECTIVE

❖ To find a job opportunity that meets my massive ambitions to optimize my knowledge and experience and put them into optimal use and optimal place with the optimal people, acquire a new knowledge and skills, deep dive and develop the new knowledge, and create a new and unprecedented knowledge.

CAREER HISTORY

Code Institute (Dublin, Ireland)

16/02/2023 - 16/08/2023

- ❖ Full Stack Developer Student
- ➤ (HTML/ CSS Essentials
- JavaScript Essentials
- Python Essentials,
- Full Stack Toolkit, Specializations: Advanced Front End, E-commerce Applications, Predictive Analytics).

Novum Hotels Sued GmbH (Hamburg, DE) Holiday Inn Express Hotel, Erlangen

01/07/2022 - 15/12/2022

- Night Manager (40 Hours/Week)
- Managing and running the whole hotel activities independently
- Managing front desk activity and handling guests' check-ins and check-outs, handling their overnight requests and processing invoices
- Processing the daily payments and preparing the daily closure reports and forecasts
- Ensuring that all end-of-day activities have been successfully executed by employees
- Balancing the cash drawer and log receipts

Wilkon e.K. (Nuremberg, DE) Quality Hotel, Erlangen

Front Office and Night Auditor (48-56 Hours/Week)

- Managing and running the whole hotel activities independently
- Managing front desk activity and handling guests' check-ins and check-outs, handling their overnight requests and processing invoices
- Preparing the daily financial reports and forecasts.
- Ensuring that all end-of-day activities have been successfully executed by employees
- Balancing the cash drawer and log receipts

Regional Freelancer (Erlangen, DE)

2015 - 01/09/2019

- Various Interpretation, Sales and Commission Based Jobs and Contracts
- ➤ Role Player and Terp with NATO and the American military (The Big Word TBW)
- Sales Executive (BAGBNB)

Johnson Controls International (Dubai, UAE)

14/03/2011 - 13/05/2014

✓ My Greatest Achievements:

I have designed, issued and edited an interactive, automated and unprecedented Finance and business intelligence bi weekly binder index consists of 300 pages for direct decisions making only. It was a revolutionary book. It had a tremendous and a great impact on the whole organization in all levels. I could save the organization millions of dollars.

Regional Finance/Sales Analyst (Gulf Region) (40 Hours/Week) 30/06/2013 – 13/05/2014 (Reporting to Regional Executive Director & FP&A Manager (Gulf Region)

Doing the same tasks of sales and market analyst in additional to financial analysis tasks which consist of:

- > Support the respective business unit leader with day-to-day activities of the business and act as the link between sales team and the business unit leader.
- Provide linkage across the different branches and business units and work closely with operational sales to collect secured revenue and gross margin information.
- Oversee all financial reports for business units and provide analysis (forecast/outlook or reality check) as required by finance.
- Prepare the monthly financial reports to be provided to the business unit leader (including P&L, TWC, SG&A).
- Review the actual financial results with the business unit leader and prepare financial bridges explaining variances to plan and forecast.
- Assist FP&A Manager and Financial Director with annual planning and forecasting process and coordinate the submissions by the various department/cost centers.
- > Finalize the weekly financial revenue tracker with the FP&A manager

> Other ad hoc request from branches and management

❖ Regional Sales & Market Analyst + SMIS Trainer (Gulf Region) (40 Hours/Week) (Reporting to Regional Executive Director (Gulf Region) 14/09/2011 - 30/06/2013

- Monitoring Sales pipelines by standing on the probabilities and the progress in comparison with the corresponding phase of customer buying process.
- Ensure reliability, validity and overall forecasts accuracy from distributors depending on product wise probabilities criteria.
- Monitoring and driving a daily follow up of AR reports by checking, reviewing and verifying the debt outstanding balance of each salesman, action owner, timeline per invoice.
- > Contributing in achieving an effective usage of MIS tools among Gulf Region on a monthly basis
- ➤ Contribute to the development of MIS tools by improving and adding new features according to business requirements.
- > Delivering integral and healthy pipelines with high percentage of accuracy all the time.
- ➤ Holding and controlling the secured volume by applying an efficient combination depends on strong and tight control, effective and convincing communication skill along with continues improvement techniques
- Reducing the variance between pipelines input and output per business unit and per geographical unit to the minimum on a monthly basis.
- Increasing the pipelines credibility and reliability by giving a confidence index for three months roll forecast.
- > Develop an AR target percentage, depends on the daily balance of overdue debt outstanding and the weekly forecasts.
- > Dynamically contributing, applying and developing interactive, creative and innovative business intelligence analysis tools.
- Training new and advanced SMIS users, by doing an effective, continues and organized training campaigns and sessions covering the gulf region.
- Preparing a various daily, weekly and monthly sales and market studies, researches and analysis.
- Initiating an account management project and training for the Gulf Region.
- Leading and working on all continuous improvement projects in Dubai

Regional Administrative Officer (40 Hours/Week) (Reporting to Parts Regional Business Manager)

14/03/2011 - 14/09/2011

- Monitoring and summarizing after-market sales transactions (Plan, Forecast, Actual...) by providing detailed reports showing statement of sales on a daily basis.
- Providing and innovative support and an intelligent assistance and solutions to After-market departments for the sake of improving the mechanism of functioning and developing work procedures.
- Providing and supporting direct manager with highly professional and creative dashboards and presentations as well, in order to facilitate reading the reports, data and figures simply, smoothly and accurately (Fostering Continues Improvement).
- > Supporting the department in day-to-day administrative work
- Processing all types of sales orders in coordination between customers (Middle East) and factories (all over the world).

✓ My Greatest Achievements:

Optimizing, automating and increasing the efficiency of the process in payable and receivable department from A to Z.

- Group Financial Accountant (48 Hours/Week) (Al Marwan Group of Companies) (Reporting to the Group Finance Manager)
- Responsible for Issuing, Preparing, Checking, Reviewing & Verifying all types of Cash Payments & Receipts, Cheque Payments & Receipts in addition to Transfer Letters (Payable & Receivable Section).
- Responsible for controlling the whole transactions in the section including (In & Out) Cash Flow & all types of cheques transactions, beside Issuing & Following up all kinds of required Daily Ledgers.
- Preparing Aging Analysis Reports.
- Responsible of preparing all Types of Petty Cash in Addition to Approving & Issuing all types of Petty Cash in the Company.
- ➤ Preparing Reconciliations between local & overseas Supplier's Statements of Account & the outstanding Statements.
- Preparing Banks Reconciliations.
- Following up the entire Supplier's Statements of Accounts (local & overseas), Invoices, Credit Notes, PO & GRN & Allocating the Due Invoices.
- Following up all the Customer's Out Standing Statements (local & overseas) & make sure that the Invoices allocated at the right time.
- Controller & responsible for the full prepayment transactions in Al Marwan Group of Companies which Includes:
- **1-** Preparing all the prepayment entries.
- **2-** Checking all the prepaid-Vouchers.
- **3-** Entering, checking & following up all the prepaid transactions in excel sheet as a backup source for my monthly prepayment reports.
- 4- Posting Prepayment Journal Vouchers on a monthly basis.
- 5- Preparing highly accurate monthly prepaid reports through Excel Sheets.
- <u>Controller of Asphalt Invoices (Internal & External)</u>, full processing according to the appropriate accounting procedures.
- (<u>Lubricants Controller</u>) which includes Checking, Auditing & Verifying all the fuel & oil slips, as well as Preparing weekly fuel & oil reports.
- Preparing all types of Journal Vouchers.

Al Khumasyah Eng. Turning and Welding Company (For Fabricating Drilling and Piling Tools) (UAE, Sharjah) 08/04/2008 - 06/07/2008

Sales & Marketing Manager (48 Hours/Week)

(Reporting to the MD & Operation Manager)

Responsible For preparing & making presentations for customers, designing new brochures, supervising and auditing the Invoices, Delivery Notes, Quotations and PO, Cost and Profit Estimator (Making schedules at excel to calculate the real Cost and the margin profit), making a daily report for sales activities and building trust and good relations with customers.

EDUCATION

❖ Bachelor Degree In Economics (Banking & Financial Sciences)
 Aleppo University - Syria

High School (As per the curriculum of UAE)
Halwan School – Sharjah

2001 - 2002

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Windows, Mac, Word, Excel, Power Point (MS Office Package) (Advanced)
- * SMIS, IScala, HFM, SQL, SAS, R, Python, Tableau, Power BI (Advanced)
- ❖ BI, KPI, Analysis (Advanced)
- Adobe Photoshop CS5 (Moderate)
- Adobe Acrobat (advanced)
- SPSS (Novice)
- Infor/Opera (Advanced)
- Shortcut (Advanced)
- Windward (Advanced)
- ❖ SAP (Advanced)
- Profit (Advanced)
- German and International Driving License B (Automatic)

LANGUAGES

English/German Fluent (Reading, writing, listening & speaking)

Arabic Mother Tongue

Korean/Spanish
Beginner (Learning stage)

ADDITIONAL ACTIVITIES

Syrian Red Crescent 2006 - 2007

Member of the Committee on Youth, Volunteer worker with a specific group which includes, implementing different workshops, attending courses in First Aid and AIDS and carried a variety of charitable activities in Aleppo branch.

Syrian Family Planning Association (SFPA) (It cooperates with UNICEF)

2005 - 2007

Member of the Committee on Youth, Social Worker, AIDS Advisor and Specialist at Youth Centre to raise awareness and advice in Aleppo branch which includes, attending & implementing different workshops, delivering a number of awareness lectures in schools & Attending lectures in Neural Linguistic Programming (NLP).

HOBBIES

Sports (Soccer, Volleyball, Basketball, Swimming, Table Tennis, Pool, Fishing, Rowing),
 Learning Languages, Movies, Series, Reading, Traveling, Meditation

REFERENCES

References Available Upon Request